Guide to the Richard W. Cutler Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Richard W. Cutler papers
1944-1995
MS 1881
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
(4 boxes)
The Richard W. Cutler papers, spanning the years 1944-2005, document Cutler's employment with the Office of Strategic Services (forerunner of the Central Intelligence Agency) during the Second World War and the immediate postwar period. They include correspondence, photographs, and other papers related to Cutler's espionage career, as well as his published memoirs, Counterspy: Memoirs of Counterintelligence Officer in World War II and the Cold War (2004).
Cutler, Richard W.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged according to format.
Biographical / Historical
Richard W. Cutler was born in New Rochelle, New York, and later moved with his family to Westport, Connecticut. He received both his B.A. (1938) and law degree (1941) from Yale University, after which he went to work for the law firm of Donovan, Leisure, Newton and Lombard in New York City. One of the firm's founding partners, Major General William "Wild Bill" Donovan, was head of the Office of Strategic Services (OSS), the forerunner of the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA). After a brief tenure at the firm, Cutler entered the U.S. Army Air Corps as a second lieutenant in 1943. Shortly thereafter, he was recruited by the OSS, and he served as an intelligence agent in London during the latter half of the Second World War. In the years immediately following the war's conclusion, Cutler was transferred to Berlin, where he continued his work for the OSS.
After his tenure with the OSS, Cutler married Elizabeth Fitzgerald and resumed his legal career, at first returning to New York City, and subsequently settling in his wife's hometown of Milwaukee, Wisconsin, where he launched a successful lifelong career in law, business and government. In 2004, Cutler published, Counterspy: Memoirs of Counterintelligence Officer in World War II and the Cold War. Cutler died on August 17, 2014.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Richard W. Cutler papers, spanning the years 1944-2005, document Cutler's employment with the Office of Strategic Services (forerunner of the Central Intelligence Agency) during the Second World War and the immediate postwar period. They include correspondence, photographs, and other papers related to Cutler's espionage career, as well as his published memoirs, Counterspy: Memoirs of Counterintelligence Officer in World War II and the Cold War (2004).
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Richard W. Cutler, 2006.
Intelligence service -- United States -- History -- 20th Century; World War, 1939-1945 -- Secret service -- United States; Cutler, Richard W.; United States. War Department. Strategic Services Unit
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1944-1995; 1
    - Behr, Elizabeth, 1944-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Cutler family
      - Cutler, Mrs. Charles [mother], 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 3-8)
      - Matthews, Betty Cutler [sister], 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Nichols, Janet Cutler [sister], 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Guttler, Barbara, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Juteau, Robertine, 1945-1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Lennington, Sidney and Wilma, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Mass" letters from Berlin [list], 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Murphy, David, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Naftali, Timothy, 1989-1996 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - OSS-SSU Berlin staff, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Perwin, Hilda (alias "Gabriel"), 1946-1947 (Box 4)
    - Polgar, Tom, 1994-2005 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    - Seiberling, Betty, 1993-1997 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Sichel, Peter, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Slater, Betty, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Strategic Services Unit friends, 1946-1950 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - Wiberg, Ingeborg [concerns Karl Johann Wiberg], 1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Willard, Anne, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Ephemera, 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photographs and photograph lists, 1944-2003 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Speeches, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Subject files
    - Broadcasts to returning soldiers aboard ship, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Geographic descriptions
      - Berlin, 1939-1946 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - London, 1939-1945 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Wiesbaden, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Kermitz, Hans, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Magazine and newspaper articles, 1945-2005 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Nazi memorabilia, 1938, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 10)